我们在试图理解如何利用程序方面已经走了很长的路。
through memory corruption.
我们已经介绍了各种各样的示例，包括基本缓冲区溢出、格式字符串
exploits and even heap exploits.
And a lot of you might already find it quite complex.
But if you put it into the context of history we are still like 16 years behind.
我们在exploit-exercises.com上探讨的最后一个例子介绍了最先进的技术
in like 2001.
虽然它仍然直接适用于廉价的嵌入式设备，比如一些物联网设备，
it’s very important to lay a foundation.
但在我们开始谈论所有这些现代剥削缓解措施和我们如何才能
绕过他们，我认为把我们学到的东西多放一点是个好主意。
abstract terms.
And try to get a feeling or an intuition about exploiting binaries.
Let’s try to create a mental model of exploitation.
But let’s first introduce some constraints, otherwise it will be too abstract.
Let’s focus on programs like we have interacted before.
this means intel architecture and on linux.
Ok.
Let’s start at the beginning.
We want programs to execute on our CPU.
That’s why a program contains assembler code - machine code.
And machine code is just like any other data in our computers.
It’s basically just bits.
0 and 1s.
A lot of times we combine them into bytes.
And a CPU can interpret a byte as an instruction.
Or multiple bytes can be interpreted as an instruction.
CPU中一些疯狂的数字硬件魔法知道这个特殊的价值
for “add the values stored in two registers and put the result in the first register.
And registers are just like small memory cells in the CPU, which fullfil different purposes.
And different architectures might have different registers for different purposes.
但是在Intel上，我们有一些通用寄存器，例如EAX和EBX，它们
a programmer is free to use however he wants to.
But there are also special registers, like EIP, the instruction pointer.
它只包含地址，地址指向内存，下一条指令
will be.
还有这个堆栈指针esp，指向堆栈的顶部，以及
the base pointer EBP, which together with the stack pointer define a stack frame.
And for beginners this might already feel complicated.
There is code, there is data, there is a stack, there is a heap.
There are functions you can call.
Functions can return.
不知何故，在堆栈上有一个返回指针，您可以用缓冲区覆盖它。
overflow.
There are a lot of different terms that we use.
But it’s a lot less complex as it may sound.
因为本质上只有两个部分很重要
we have memory, which is just a huuuuuuge space of bits that can be 1 or 0.
Usually we group them in bytes or words.
还有一个CPU，它有一个定义良好的确定性行为，可以对它进行操作。
memory.
It’s really that simple.
Well.
关键在于实际细节，但本质上，当CPU打开时，它
will start at some defined address.
This could be 0, but could also be defined to be something else.
它请求来自某个RAM的内存内容，查看存储在该地址的值，
and performs the action according to whatever that value represents.
现在，当我们要执行一个程序时，不能直接将代码写入
RAM, and restart the CPU at address 0.
Because if your program would cause an endless loop, the whole system would stop working.
但是当你编程一个Arduino，一个小微控制器时，基本上就是你
do.
But that’s why some people developed something like the Linux kernel.
它为您抽象出直接的硬件，并确保如果您的程序不好，
you don’t kill the whole system.
That’s why a program is not just plain assembler code, but it’s a fairly complex file format.
An ELF file.
Which does contain your raw code, but also a lot of other information.
当你执行这个程序时，Linux系统会打开elf文件，读取
并解释所有必要的元数据并为您设置执行环境，以及
then jumps to the start of your actual code.
那么执行环境是什么样子的呢？
这一点很重要，因为在这种环境中，你试图利用程序，
you need to understand it.
And in some way it’s actyually very simple.
Again, the devil is in the practical details, but it will make sense.
Let’s say the CPU is just about to execute your first instruction.
This means the kernel and the hardware magic has already set up everything.
And this is how it looks like.
You have a big blob of memory.
It ranges from 0, to ffffff.
In reality you don’t really have that much memory, that’s why we call it virtual memory.
看起来你拥有所有的内存，但是硬件的魔力只会让你觉得你拥有
it.
But in anyway, the CPU now executes your program which is somewhere in that huge memory.
Let’s have a look at how this memory is divided up in a real program.
例如，在这里，我们看到从这个起始地址到这个结束地址，
program is mapped.
我们说是映射的，因为它实际上不在这个地址，但如果你愿意的话，它就在那里。
read the value from that address, in your assembler code.
所以忽略了底层的物质现实，只是接受了这个巨大的范围
of memory you can work with.
And infact the stack is also just here.
It’s also just defined as starting from this address and ends at this address.
所以堆栈并没有真正的增长或收缩，这只是计算机理论模型。
of a stack.
但是堆栈实际上是如何定义的呢？
CPU有堆栈寄存器esp，它将包含一个指向
this area here.
So could you just point the stack pointer somewhere else.
就像你的代码？
是啊！
You absolutely could.
堆栈指针没有什么特别的，它只是一个包含地址的寄存器，
and it could contain any address.
What makes ESP actually special is just that it does some fancy stuff based on instructions.
例如，pop eax指令将查找存储在该位置的值
where ESP points to, usually that’s the stack, but doesn’t have to.
And then writes the value from that location into the eax register.
And you can absolutely abuse that in an exploit.
例如，如果您发现一个bug，它允许您将堆栈指针设置为
value, you could create a fake stack on the heap, and just point ESP there.
Often times referred to as a stack pivot.
因此，失去你在计算机科学中所学的一堆不断增长和缩小的精神图像，
and just think of it what it really is.
It’s just some memory where the ESP register points to.
And instructions cause interesting effects based on that register.
And in the same sense the instruction pointer is not special.
Usually it points into your code, but it doesn’t have to.
If you manage to control EIP somehow, you can just point it to other memory.
For example the stack, which we have used in previous exploits.
Because we placed data that is actually valid assembler code onto the stack.
You know it as shellcode.
The CPU doesn’t care.
EIP寄存器指向一些内存，CPU很高兴地完成这些值。
say.
And well, that is just half true.
因为正如您可能知道的，在现代系统中，堆栈不再是可执行的，所以
CPU does kinda care, but also not really.
It just means that certain areas in this memory can have different permissions.
某些区域具有可执行标记，这意味着CPU允许EIP指向该区域，并且
乐于将这些值解释为指令，但堆栈等其他区域没有
it.
And then the CPU refuses to interpret it as instructions.
现在，当我们更接近于所有这些不同的数据中包含了什么类型的数据时
memory areas, we can try to come up with creative ways of how to abuse the.
One example is the typical stack structure.
当CPU执行一条调用指令时，它将放置当前指令指针值
at the address where the stack pointer points to.
It places it ontop of the stack.
当函数返回时，它获取堆栈指针指向和的值。
sets the instruction pointer to it.
因此，如果您设法在堆栈上修改这个值，您可以控制到什么EIP
将设置为函数返回的时间，因此您可以决定执行什么操作
next.
That’s a classical buffer overflow.
另一个有趣的数据结构是全局偏移表，它基本上只是
内存中包含指向函数的指针的区域，如果覆盖其中的条目，也可以
控制如果调用的函数引用的地址来自
this table.
我的意思是，通常你不能直接覆盖这些值，但这只是意味着你有
to become creative.
For example think of two objects on the heap.
A user object and a name object, and the user object has a pointer to the name object.
当您想更改这个用户的名称时，代码将跟随指针并
将新名称写入该位置，这意味着如果您可以以某种方式覆盖该指针，
you can control where it would write the name to.
所以我们可以用堆栈上的地址覆盖名称指针，当我们写
用户的新名称，我们将实际覆盖存储的指令指针
the stack.
看到我想说什么了吗？
There is memory that contains data.
Some restrictions apply, like certain memory areas are not writeable, others are not executable.
And there is a CPU that is very dumb and just executes whatever EIP points to.
And there is a program in the memory, which the CPU executes.
And this code uses the memory to do whatever it is supposed to do.
And it trusts in a certain integrity of the data in memory.
但是如果有一个bug，它允许你改变内存中的一个值，程序
did not intend to be modifiable, amazing things could happen.
And what can happen, that’s just limited by your creativity and imagination.
内存中的一个更改的字节可能会导致某段代码意外写入
覆盖对象的函数指针的位置，代码的另一部分
wanted to use, and suddenly executes something very different.
我们将这些技术命名为堆栈缓冲区溢出、堆风水，
免费使用ROP，都是解决内存中数据问题的创造性方法
the program executed by the CPU reacts to it.
I understand that this episode might not have contained actual useful information to you.
但我有点想把它拿出来，因为也许有人不太喜欢看电视节目
and exploits in this way.
But I hope you can see the value in this way of thinking about it.
I think it takes some away some of the fear that it all looks so complicated.
I’m really interested to hear your critical opinion about this.
So comment here on youtube or on the reddit thread linked below.
但无论你是否喜欢，我们很快就会继续我们的学习之路
more advanced memory corruption techniques.
So, stay curious, and see you next time.